Finding Aid for the Medical Artifacts Collection
Eskind Biomedical Library Manuscripts Collection
Medical Artifacts Collection
multiple
Eskind Biomedical Library Manuscripts Collection
EBL-0000
1 linear_feet
- Box 18 1 Drugs peddled by native medicine men of French Morocco. Three phials containing: a) worm seeds for worm cures, b) iron fillings for the eyes, c) pebbles for the heart. Donated by Miss Eleanor Fair, Metropolitan Life Insurance Co., New York, 1938.
- Box 82 3 Mortar (stone) and pestle (stone with wooden handle). This type of mortar was used in doctors' offices in rural areas throughout the nineteenth century. Used by William P. Moseley and his son in Buckingham County, Virginia, 1818-1896. Dr. Shelley noted: "Probably Italian and several centuries old."
- Box 18 5 Indian Turnip. Sliced and eaten with salt this was widely used as an aphrodisiac in the U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. These objects represent objects relating to popular medicine, collected by doctors in the rural South. One of them, Dr. Sam Morris of Alabama, was a black physician who collected many amulets and medicines from black southerners. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 18 6 Bottle containing hog-hoof (pigs' toe nails). Tea made from this was used to cure pneumonia, bronchitis and flu. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. These objects represent objects relating to popular medicine, collected by doctors in the rural South. One of them, Dr. Sam Morris of Alabama, was a black physician who collected many amulets and medicines from black southerners. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 18 7 Bottle with pellets of sheeps' dung. Tea made from this was used to make measles break out. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. These objects represent objects relating to popular medicine, collected by doctors in the rural South. One of them, Dr. Sam Morris of Alabama, was a black physician who collected many amulets and medicines from black southerners. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 18 8 Yellow-root. A decoction made from this was used for purgation and stomach disorders. When worn in a bag hung from the neck, it was expected to prevent all intestinal diseases. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. These objects represent objects relating to popular medicine, collected by doctors in the rural South. One of them, Dr. Sam Morris of Alabama, was a black physician who collected many amulets and medicines from black southerners. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 9 Branches of witch-hazel. Decoctions from which were used as effective abortifacients. Collected by Dr. Sam Morris (black physician), Alabama. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. These objects represent objects relating to popular medicine, collected by doctors in the rural South. One of them, Dr. Sam Morris of Alabama, was a black physician who collected many amulets and medicines from black southerners. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 10 Tooth of some animal. Suspended from the neck, it was to insure victory over enemies. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. These objects represent objects relating to popular medicine, collected by doctors in the rural South. One of them, Dr. Sam Morris of Alabama, was a black physician who collected many amulets and medicines from black southerners. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 11 "John the Conqueror." A piece of jointed root of an unidentified plant, to be chewed and spat out just before undertaking any severe task. It is believed to insure success in labor, lobe and battle. Collected by Dr. Sam Morris, Alabama. U.S. rural South, Early 20th century. These objects represent objects relating to popular medicine, collected by doctors in the rural South. One of them, Dr. Sam Morris of Alabama, was a black physician who collected many amulets and medicines from black southerners. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 12 Yellow-root. A decoction made from this was used for purgation and stomach disorders. When worn in a bag hung from the neck, it was expected to prevent all intestinal diseases. Collected by Dr. Sam Morris, Alabama. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. These objects represent objects relating to popular medicine, collected by doctors in the rural South. One of them, Dr. Sam Morris of Alabama, was a black physician who collected many amulets and medicines from black southerners. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 13 Indian turnip. Sliced and eaten with salt, it is widely used as an aphrodisiac. Collected by Dr. Sam Morris, Alabama. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. These objects represent objects relating to popular medicine, collected by doctors in the rural South. One of them, Dr. Sam Morris of Alabama, was a black physician who collected many amulets and medicines from black southerners. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 14 Irish Potatoes (2). A black man nearing 80 used these two Irish potatoes for ten years or more as an effective preventative against rheumatism and lumbago -- one for each disease. They are dry without being brittle, and seem petrified. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. These objects represent objects relating to popular medicine, collected by doctors in the rural South. One of them, Dr. Sam Morris of Alabama, was a black physician who collected many amulets and medicines from black southerners. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 15 Sheeps' dung. Tea made from this was used to make measles break out. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. These objects represent objects relating to popular medicine, collected by doctors in the rural South. One of them, Dr. Sam Morris of Alabama, was a black physician who collected many amulets and medicines from black southerners. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 16 Coin (U.S. half dollar). Removed from the oesophageal constriction of a black woman who had accidentally swallowed it. She claimed to have used it successfully as an unfailing contraceptive measure, merely by retaining it in the mouth during coition. The coin had been conjured by an old conjuring man. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. These objects represent objects relating to popular medicine, collected by doctors in the rural South. One of them, Dr. Sam Morris of Alabama, was a black physician who collected many amulets and medicines from black southerners. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 17 Mole foot. Worn suspended from the neck to prevent venereal diseases. Collected by Dr. Sam Thelford, Boligee, Greene County, Alabama. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. These objects represent objects relating to popular medicine, collected by doctors in the rural South. One of them, Dr. Sam Morris of Alabama, was a black physician who collected many amulets and medicines from black southerners. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 18 French silver franc worn by black woman of 75 on a cord around waist for ten years to "prevent being conjured." She believed that without it she would have been dead. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. These objects represent objects relating to popular medicine, collected by doctors in the rural South. One of them, Dr. Sam Morris of Alabama, was a black physician who collected many amulets and medicines from black southerners. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 19 Half-dime (U.S.). Worn about the ankle by a black woman for twelve years to attract and retain lovers. Collected by B. B. Sims, Talladega, Alabama. U. S. rural South. Early 20th century. These objects represent objects relating to popular medicine, collected by doctors in the rural South. One of them, Dr. Sam Morris of Alabama, was a black physician who collected many amulets and medicines from black southerners. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 82 20 Obstetrical forceps, ca. 1870.
- Box 18 21 Pill tile. Used in the practice of medicine in the U.S. 19th century. Donated by Dr. P. E. Tucker, Buckingham County, Virginia.
- Box 21 22 Prescription scale. Portable scale marketed under the name of Dr. C. F. Fitch. Patented September 29, 1885. Small rectangular chrome-plated metal box with a balancing slide rule attached to a spoon. Previous card stated: "Measuring weighing machine. Used in the practice of medicine in the U.S. during the period 1800-1896. Used by Dr. William P. Moseley of Buckingham Co., Virginia. (He had three sons in the Confederate Army: Col. W. P., Col. Edgar, and Captain Samuel P. Moseley)." Note: Stored with object #39 Donated by Mrs. Moseley Smith, through the courtesy of Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 21 23 Two single-bladed scarificators or spring lancets. Used for blood-letting in the practice of medicine until the end of the 19th century. Used by Dr. William P. Moseley of Buckingham County, Virginia. Note: the blade is broken on one of the scarificators. Donated by Mrs. Moseley Smith, through the courtesy of Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 4 24 Nitze Cystoscope. Ca. 1930. Donated by Dr. Harry Shelley.
- Box 21 26 Two drug boxes U.S. 19th and early 20th century. Round.
- Box 17 27 Buzzard quills and copper amulet used to make teething easy. Collected by Dr. W. H. Harper, Selma, Alabama. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 28 Copper amulet used to make teething easy. Collected by Dr. W. H. Harper, Selma, Alabama. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 29 Rabbit tobacco -- worn as a charm to prevent asthma. A decoction made from this plant was used for the treatment of asthma. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 30 Mole feet. A charm worn to ease teething. Copper pennies were supposed to neutralize baby scents. Collected by Dr. W. H. Harper, Selma, Alabama. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 31 May apple root, the tea of which is used for all forms of "stomach trouble.” Collected and donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison, Birmingham, Alabama. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 32 Copper wire worn on the wrist to prevent all sickness and insure physical strength. Collected by Dr. Sam Thelford, Boligee, Greene County, Alabama. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 33 Buckeyes, worn on cord about the waist to prevent heart disease and to win the love of young women. Also used to prevent hemorrhoids. Collected and donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison, Birmingham, Alabama. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 34 Copper penny and some unidentified bits of wood. A charm to make teething easy. Collected by Dr. W. H. Harper, Selma, Alabama. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 35 Copper pennies (two). These coins were worn around the neck by a black woman, age 45, as a neuralgic prophylaxis. They were reputed to have cured an attack; however, in the meantime some bad teeth had been removed. Collected by H. S. Castleman, Sylacauga, Alabama. U.S. rural south. Early 20th century. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 36 Cloth-covered string. String worn by white male, age 34, who had used it at the suggestion of an acquaintance, who claimed that such a string saturated with turpentine and tied around the waist would cure chills and fever. When the string was removed the man's rectal temperature was 106.3 which was three or four hours after the malarial paroxysm. Members of this man's family were infected with malaria, and he was not well and had been advised to take treatment, which he ignored. He admitted that he had been tortured the night before by the turpentine saturated string. Proper treatment for malaria promptly controlled the situation. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 17 37 Amulet of small cotton bag and two beads of unidentified substance. Said "to keep the blues away." Collected by Dr. W. H. Harper, Selma, Alabama. U.S. rural South. Early 20th century. Donated by Dr. William Groce Harrison.
- Box 33 38 Plaster cast of the hand of Dr. Barney Brooks. Original plaster-cast of the hand of Dr. Barney Brooks, prepared by the son of Dr. Mims at the request of Dr. Allen Whipple for his "Collection of Model Hands of Famous Surgeons" in Columbia University. Donated by Dr. Barney Brooks, December 3, 1951.
- Box 21 39 Saddle-bag scales (for weighing medicines). Wooden box with brass post and slide out drawer for scales. Early to mid-nineteenth century. Donated by Mrs. Florence Pratt of Buckingham Court House, Virginia. Note: Objects #122 and #39 are stored with it.
- Box 37 40 Box containing a surgeon's instruments. Two saws, three knives, two other instruments, and two needles. It contains space for three additional instruments which are missing.
- Box 2 41 Saddle-bags made of leather, with leather loops inside to hold medicine bottles. Contains five bottles, some with powders, Some with dried liquids. Used by Dr. William P. Moseley of Buckingham County, Virginia, for fifty years. U.S. Nineteenth century. Her husband used these saddlebags as well as the instruments listed in this inventory in practice. He Was born May 31, 1794 and died April 2, 1863. He attended the University of Virginia from 1816-17, and graduated in medicine from the University of Pennsylvania. He lived and practiced in Buckingham Co., Virginia. His three sons: Col. William P.; Lieut. Col. Edgar F.; and Capt. Samuel P. fought in the Confederate army. Donated by Mrs. William Moseley Smith.
- Box 36 42 Pocket case of old surgical instruments used by Dr. John A. Tillow, Hendersonville, Tennessee about 1870. Donated by his grandson Mr. Bransford Stone, November 10, 1942. Donated by Bransford Stone.
- Box 5 43 Scarificator. Belonged to Dr. William P. Moseley, Buckingham County, Virginia. Donated by Mrs. William Moseley Smith.
- Box 4 44 Instrument case of Dr. William P. Moseley of Buckingham County, Virginia. Case is of red leather and contains eight instruments; six instruments are apparently missing. Donated by Mrs. William Moseley Smith.
- Box 21 45 Wooden box containing two medicine scales and six weights. Used by Dr. Arthur Moseley of Buckingham Co., Virginia. Donated by Mrs. William Moseley Smith.
- Box 51 46 Chinese ivory figurine from the interior of China, obtained by Miss Mary Cutter from a Chinese physician. It was used for women patients in this manner: Modesty on part of the patient and custom forbade a personal examination; so the patient indicated on the ivory figurine the location of the pain, and the physician then prescribed. Such figurines were formerly in general use in China and still are in certain sections. Figurine is quite old (ca. 1800) and very rare. Donated by Dr. Cobb Pilcher.
- Box 37 47 Wooden case lined with velvet, containing operating set (seven instruments) belonging to Dr. W. M. Cunningham. Dating from 1890, it was used by him in a double amputation of a patient's legs below the knee in a waiting room of a railroad station, using a caboose cushion on the floor for an operating table. The patient, Rufe Bivens, lived many years thereafter as a useful citizen.
- Safe 48 Sinhalese Ola (palm-leaf manuscript). Written on the prepared leaves of the Palmyra Palm (Borasus flabellifer) about 1745 A.D. The text is translated chiefly from the original Sanskrit writings of Charka into a mixture of Sinhalese prose and verse, dealing with various medical subjects. A part of the work is missing. Wooden covers are lacquered, and, like the binding cord and medallion (broken and in separate box) are also modern, but made by Kandyan workmen after antique models. Donated by Dr. Casey Wood, Chicago, January 8, 1927.
- Box 6 49 Box containing three lancets. Two used by Dr. Mathieu Derivaux. The third, a cupping lancet, was used by Dr. J. O. Kirkpatrick, Nashville. All three lancets are folded between two leaves of tortoise shell.
- Box 36 50 Civil War Era Surgical Instruments. Two instruments (folded between tortoise shell leaves) from a pocket case of instruments purchased in 1859 and used through the Civil War and afterward by Dr. J. T. Harrison, Talladega, Alabama. He graduated from the University of Nashville in 1855.
- Box 50 51 Portraits of Vanderbilt Chancellor Carmichael and Dean Leathers Wooden box, 11" x 14," containing two portraits of Vanderbilt Chancellor Carmichael and Dean Leathers presented to Lt. Col. George W. Reyer, Commanding Officer of the 300th General Hospital.
- Box 11 52 Truax surgical pump 1890, made by Truax Greene & Co., Chicago Ill. Used for aspirating or irrigating cavities: "Stiff rubber tubing is inserted, then turn the crank forwards or backwards for the results desired."
- Box 51 53 Wooden case, velvet lined, with ten surgical instruments (one or possibly more missing). Instruments were given as the prize in surgery by Dr. Briggs, the professor to Robert Lee Vaught of Mason County, West Virginia, at his graduation on February 25, 1886. Dr. Vaught settled in Chattanooga as a general practitioner, specializing in surgery. Soon after he settled, he was elected Professor of Anatomy in the Chattanooga Medical College, a position he held until his death on August 28 1895 when he drowned in the Great Kanawha River while enroute to visit his mother. He was born May 24, 1863.
- Safe 55A Bronze medallion of the Johns Hopkins Hospital, to commemorate fifty years of service to humanity, science, and education 1889-1939.
- Safe 55B Bronze medallion of William Beaumont 1785-1853, XIII International Physiological Congress, Boston, 1929.
- Safe 55C Bronze medallion of Stephen Smith, founder of the American Public Health Association, commissioned to commemorate the semicentennial meeting of the association in 1922.
- Safe 55D Bronze medallion of Frank Billings, Dean of the Faculty, Rush Medical College, 1924.
- Safe 55E Bronze medal with pin and ribbon from the Tennessee State Medical Association 1930 annual convention in Nashville and commissioned to commemorate their centennial celebration.
- Box 56 56 Wooden box, velvet lined, containing enema from the Truss Works, Sheffield, England.
- Box 18 57 Ear speculum "before the days of light." Donated by Dr. J. B. Hibbitts, Jr.
- Box 5 58 Korean medical instruments. Bone tube with meander- patterned metal cap, containing one large knife - "Chine," and three needle-like small "chines.” The large chine is used to open abscesses. The small chines are stuck into certain parts of the flesh for various purposes. Contained in blue cardboard box.
- Box 5 59-72 Korean herb doctor's drugs. Note: The drugs described on the following cards are used by Korean herb doctors. Besides regular medical doctors, there are two types of herb doctors in Korea. The older type, which still flourishes in rural areas, is learned through an apprenticeship. The modern type, which is licensed by the government, requires a student, who has attained the equivalent of a high school education, to study pharmacology in an institution. Largely, herbal medicine is taught there, but western pharmacology is taught also. It appears that the herbal medicines in this collection derive from the old-type of herb doctor. These Korean herbal medicines come in their original paper bags, and are imprinted with their names in Chinese characters. The herb medicines were introduced from China and retain their Chinese names. The small paper envelopes, imprinted with Korean characters, were merely used as containers for the want of others: they derive from the Graham Tuberculosis Sanatorium (Korean name: Kwang Ju Chai Joong). The drugs are not from the hospital.
- Shelf 15 137 Framed University of Nashville Medical School diploma for Robert Dozier 1900.
- Shelf 13 138 Alpha Kappa Kappa Charter to Vanderbilt, 1903, Framed.
- Shelf 15 139 Abbey, Daniel. University of Nashville Medical School diploma for Daniel Abbey, 1855. Framed.
- Shelf 15 142 Whitfield, Harrison. Medical Society of the University of Nashville diploma of membership for Harrison Whitfield, 1858. Framed. Donated by Mr. James Bass, Vice President of American Airlines.
- Shelf 15 143 Whitfield, Harrison. University of Nashville Doctor of Medicine diploma of Harrison Whitfield, 1858. Framed. Donated by Mr James Bass, Vice-President, American Airlines.
- Shelf 24 174 Vanderbilt University Medical Department. Framed photograph of Senior Class and Faculty, Medical Department, Vanderbilt University, 1915-1916. Donated by Dr. C. Richard Treadway, January 31, 1978.
- Safe 185 Carroll, John. Thirty-nine paintings of patients' arms, legs, and faces demonstrating pellagrous lesions. Ink and water color drawings executed by artist J. C. (John Carroll) in connection with Dr. Joseph Goldberger's work with Pellagrines in South Carolina. Each painting is accompanied with Dr Goldberger's handwritten notes on the case. Donated by William J, Darby for Dr. Arnold E. Schaefer, June 11, 1979.
- Box 74 217 Williams, Cicely. Audio tape, magnetic one reel, of “Story of Kwashiorkor” by Dr. Cicely Williams. History of Medicine Society Lecture, December 3, 1968. 1_ I.P.S. Donated by Dr. E. N. Todhunter, January 1980.
- Shelf 24 218 Vanderbilt University Department of Dentistry. Framed composite of the Faculty and Graduates of the Department of Dentistry of Vanderbilt University, 1901.
- Map Case Drawer 7 260 Pulliam, Columbus Alonzo Monroe. Diploma for the Doctor of Medicine degree from the University of Nashville awarded to C. A. M. Pulliam, March 1, 1860. Parchment and written in Latin. Donated by Richard Montgomery, January 5, 1981.
- Map Case Drawer 7 261 Pulliam, Columbus Alonzo Monroe Medical Society Certificate from the University of Nashville awarded to C.A.M. Pulliam. Parchment, written in Latin, and signed by W.K. Bowling, President of the society. Donated by Richard Montgomery January 5, 1981.
- Map Case Drawer 7 262 Pulliam, Columbus Alonzo Monroe. University of Nashville Certificate of Honor awarded to C.A.M. Pulliam, February 24, 1860. Signed by John Berrien Lindsley. Donated by Richard Montgomery, January 5, 1981.
- Map Case Drawer 1 305 Goldberger, Joseph. Signed photograph of Dr. Joseph Goldberger, mounted and laminated. Donated by Dr. J.H. Browe, 1985.
- Safe 306 Carroll, John. Painting by John Carroll of a woman facing left with her hands on her lap and suffering from pellagra. Ca. 1918. Laminated. Donated by Dr. J. H. Browe, 1985.
- Map Case Shelf 2 307 Boothe, Archabale Alexander. Diploma for the Doctor of Medicine degree from Vanderbilt University awarded to Archabale Alexander Boothe, March 1, 1876. Parchment and written in Latin. Rolled and contained in a card board tube. Donated by Judith Hazlewood, Librarian Luther L. Gobbel Library Lambuth College, Jackson Tennessee, 1985. Added to inventory August 28, 1995. Donated by Luther L. Gobbel Library, Lambuth College
- Map Case Shelf 2 308 Boothe, Archabale Alexander. Diploma for the Doctor of Medicine degree from Vanderbilt University awarded to Archabale Alexander Boothe, 1875. Parchment and written in Latin. Rolled and contained in a card board tube. Donated by Judith Hazlewood, Librarian Luther L. Gobbel Library Lambuth College, Jackson Tennessee, 1985. Added to inventory August 28, 1995. Donated by Luther L. Gobbel Library, Lambuth College
- Map Case Shelf 2 309 Boothe, Archabale Alexander. Temporary diploma for the Doctor of Medicine degree from Vanderbilt University awarded to Archabale Alexander Boothe, March, 1875. Rolled and contained in a card board tube. Donated by Judith Hazlewood, Librarian Luther L Gobbel Library Lambuth College, Jackson Tennessee, 1985. Added to inventory August 28, 1995. Donated by Luther L. Gobbel Library, Lambuth College